[Music]
hi this is about stem from coding the
smart way comm and today in this video
tutorial I show you how to build a real
world web application by only using
Toyama script so we will not make use of
any other modern web frameworks like
angular react of UJS we will only use
poor JavaScript and by following this
tutorial you will be able to learn the
basics and build a real-world
application so stay tuned okay so let's
take a look at the sample application we
are going to build in this video
tutorial and you can see it here it's a
central issue tracker application where
you can put in some issues may be issues
with a regarding software product and
you can describe each issues by using
that input form here and we have input
controls available for putting in a
description text you can choose a
severity here from a list of low medium
and high and you can use the assigned to
field of entering a name who is
responsible for maybe
solving that issue so let's try it out
maybe we will use as a description here
delete function in product it's not
working and we choose severity medium
and enter my name assigned to and then I
can use the button head and you can see
it immediately here shown in the bottom
section of our application and you can
see all the issue is shown here with
status information so initially we are
setting each issue to status open and
you can see we have two user actions
defined here by including two buttons
see the user can choose to click on
button close and by using the close
button you can see the issue is put to
use status closed
maybe we can enter a second one so let's
use second issue we put it too low and
[Music]
let's use another name here and you can
see it's automatically added here to the
list and now again it's put to open
because of the initial status and you
can see here is the severity here is the
assigned to name shown and the second
user action we have included here is the
delete button the user can click on and
by using the delete button he or she is
able to remove that item from the list
here okay so let's stop with
implementing the sample application step
by step and we will only use JavaScript
and we will make no use of framework
like angular and react and UK has
already set so let's start right away
I switch over to the terminal and let's
first get the project setup done and I
start by creating a new folder a new
project folder so make your J's app a
one okay let's change into that folder
and then we do need two files here and
so on we will keep things easy one file
is it's our HTML file index.html and the
second file is main dot KS ok so here we
are ok so let's start on the source code
editor and in my case
on using Adam okay here we are so and
let's start with opening index.html and
start implementation and we will first
do a very basic implementation of
index.html so what do we need of course
we need an HTML tag okay then we need a
head section we need a body section of
course and within the head section let's
just say that we want to have a meter
element and we'll use that to put our
character set so cut care set equal to
the string UTF - 8 okay and we will use
the head section for defining a title
okay let's name it
young script turn issue Karaka is the
title of our application and okay let's
use a doctype of HTML and complete the
first implementation by including in the
body section script text and with the
script tag we have the option of
including our our main GS file where the
other script code of our application
goes into okay so main dot jf okay so
the next step we need to take is to
include the bootstrap framework in our
application and maybe you you saw it
from the user interface I showed you we
are using the bootstrap
CSS classes to include them as styling
in our application so it does not affect
our our implementation in playing the
other script it's only used for of
styling our user interface so that we
can concentrate on on implementing our
Yahoo script based web application and
the easiest way of including now the
bootstrap framework here is to go to get
bootstrap comms and here on the web side
you can see here is the button download
bootstrap let's let's click on that
button and here on that page you will
see an overview of various possibilities
of how to include bootstrap in your
project the easiest way is to just use
bootstrap from a content delivery
network so woods web CDN is affection we
um we are concentrating on and you can
see if we want to include it from a
content delivery network we need to
include the three things in our
application we need to include a link
element which points to the stylesheet
bootstrap mndot CS CSS and we need to
include another link element which
points to the bootstrap - a theme dot
MnDOT the CSS but this is optional this
is only needed if we want to use seaming
we do not want to use seaming in our
application so I do not need to include
the second thing you but I need to
institute the script element here that
is pointing to the RS code file of
bootstrap so let's do it let's first
[Music]
copy that link element and we will place
place a link element in rehab
here okay
then take the script element copy it go
back to Adam and include it here in the
body section okay okay the bootstrap
framework has one dependency and it
needs jQuery so we need to include
jQuery as well here in our project and
again we are using it from a content
delivery network so let's switch over
and open another website and the website
we need is code dot J query comm and you
will find the jQuery core library here
and we would like to use version a three
point X and the minified version so
let's click on it and you will get with
the script tag we need to include in our
application you will get it here and you
can simply copy it to the clipboard and
then switch back to Adam and include it
now let's include it here okay then
there is another dependency we do need
and that is the small library which is
called chance Jas
the website is the Weibull at chance
jegs.com and that library will only use
it for one special task because we would
like to generate global unique
identifiers for each of the issue
entries we are creating an our
application and creating global unique
event
first is something this library is
providing for us by simply using a
function put as you can see here and we
will use that function later on and now
we need to make sure that this library
is included and you will find that the
meaningful minified version here and if
I click on it we can take that URL here
and go back to Adam and include another
another script X with source set to that
URL ok so that's all what's needed to
hear I'll get early dependency which are
used and that is the core implementation
of index dot HTML ok next thing is to
bring some content here into our body
section and I do so by starting with
this section and the dis section we'll
get to find a class of container that
the bootstrap class of course and within
the big section let's start by adding a
heading and the heading should be J as
issue tracker and let's include small
small tag by coding smart way calm okay
so let's uncheck index dot HTML in the
browser and you can do so by switching
over to the command line and I'm using a
web server here and the web server the
development web server I'm you
is called life life server so that is
the command using that command I can
start up the web server if you have not
installed live server on your system you
can do so by simply installing it from
bio npm just type in npm install - g for
installing it globally on your system
and then use a package name live server
so that would either command to install
it i have already installed live server
so i'm not going to execute this right
now instead I'm starting with serve up
okay and you can see it's automatically
loading on the website here on the
browser so here you can see my headline
so let's see what's the advantage of
using live server I will put it here as
side-by-side so live server as a name
already promises is a development web
server with live reload capability so
what does it mean I can for example now
change something here my code face it
and you can see the web site was the
change
included with the changed output here is
reloaded immediate immediately I do not
need to reload it manually it's just
there so it's very easy to use it side
by side was my code editor I can see
immediately on what changes I am
implementing here in the code I can see
those changes reflected here in the
website okay so let's take that out so
okay let's continue on the
implementation just here under our
headline we now want to include on the
HTML elements we do need for the form
and the input form should be embedded in
another dysfunction so what
in okay and we give it a class of
Jumbotron
okay that's again a bootstrap CSS class
and within that this section or let's
include another headline and let's give
it a headline of add new issue and then
bring in the form element okay so we do
not need the action attribute here
instead we need to assign an ID and let
it use the ID of issue input form okay
and within our form element we will use
three disk sections with a class form
- group assigned so let's bring them in
okay that's the first one class form -
group okay and for the first input
element let's use a label and the label
is for the input element which gets
assigned of the ID of issue description
input and we give it a label of
description okay next the input element
and the input element for Ally
description of course should be of type
text we need a class of form control
okay then we need to assign VI d which
is issue discourage input okay and maybe
like this one place over here and the
place over the text should be describe
the issue okay so that's the first
fungal now we can take a better section
here is the fungal section copy it one
two so that we have three deep sections
with class form this group assigned
included here in our form and now we
adapt the second this section here
that's the input section which should be
used for let's see what do we need we do
need the similarity so let's give it the
label of severity and change the ID here
for which the label is for to issue the
rarity input okay and next we do need
the input element here that's text again
[Music]
no not in that case in that case we do
need to have something this one here so
we can remove it okay because we want to
have a selection list so that the user
can choose from the options low medium
and high and to implement such a
drop-down list we use the Select element
and set and the Select element gets the
ID of issue severity input
and then within the Select element we do
need to include three times the option
element okay option
don't forget the end here so it's option
with the value of low that's the first
option and the description of low here
and last let's copy it okay then we have
medium with a label medium then we have
to value high with the list entry high
okay so here we are
whoo okay so we need to assign a class
here as well which is the class form
control once again so and you can see
here as we are typing in the HTML code
the output here here Nam in our browser
window updates automatically and we can
check right there that the drop-down
list for example is already implemented
correctly and showing the values low
medium and high we have specified here
and now we need to we need to adapt the
third section here the third form and
group and that's the input element for
the assigned to value so let's adapt the
label okay so that's again text we're
using the input element here we assign
the class form - control and the IDS
again issue assigned to input
placeholder let's check
- and possible okay so here we are let's
the form implemented you can see the
form is there it's embedded in a
Jumbotron that's indicated here at the
gray by the gray background color and
then we have the headline and we have
three input elements the description
which is of type text with the drop down
list for the severity value and we have
again a text here for the side - okay so
one thing an our forum is as missing and
we do need to include a submit button at
the bottom of our form because we do
want to have a button away verses of the
user can click on the submit button and
add the new issue entry - to the list of
issues basically so let's include it
here on right before the closing form
text and we are using the button element
okay and the button element gets the
type which is submit in that case and it
gets assigned again class and we are
using actually two classes here we are
using the button class and the button -
primary class which gives us a result
the blue colored button from okay and
let's say that the button should contain
a light LED okay here we are
that is the button and now we need to
include a few more things here right
under the this section of the Jumbotron
so one with continued implementation
here and let's card was implementing a
new dissection and what this section
should be
of class called s - LG 12 so that we use
some all the 12 columns label on our
layout and within that we are defining
another dis section and we're using the
ID attribute to assign an ID of issues
list here okay that's all for now that
this section will remain empty because
we do only want to use it later on in
our Yama script implementation when we
are iterating over the list of issues
and generating the HTML output we have
the possibility of retrieving that this
element here by retrieving it by using
that ID here issues list and then we are
inserting the content the HTML content
here which is negative output all the
lists all the issues in our list of
issues and that HTML code will be
generated dynamically in our Yahoo
script code so that following later on
so let's include one more thing here
let's define another discussion and this
time we are using a class of
footer and within the footer let's use a
paragraph element and then we say okay
copy coding this mod wacom save it and
you can see here is the result and yeah
that's that's all we need here in
index.html so far
next thing else to implement the llaves
code part of our application okay then
let's switch over to our second file in
the project directory and that is
. jf and start implementation with a
function which is called fetch issues
and read function should be used to
fetch the list of issues already on a
Weibull and then as a data store and our
application I would like to use the
browser's local storage so that's the
place that is a storage location where
we will put issues which the user enters
by using the form and that's a place we
need to retrieve issues when the
application starts and as we do need to
retrieve issues as in various points in
time so for example after the
application has been loaded we will
implement the function which we can
later on call multiple times and that
function is called fresh issues and if
it supplies know where we put in the
implementation which is fetching issue
items from local storage and we start
with the program code so let's define
here a variable of the name issues and
that should be equal to the result of
Jason dot path and we are passing the
return value from local storage get item
and the item we would like to retrieve
from local storage is the item within
named issues okay next we will retrieve
reference
a reference to the dissection we
declared in index dot HTML which helps
the ID of issues list aside and in the
other script we can do so by using
document in calling the function get
element by ID and then passing in the ID
of the disk section and legacy issues
list
okay so let's initialize the content and
make sure that the the content of that
div element is empty and we can set the
content by using a property which is
called in our HTML and we set it just an
empty string to make that sure okay okay
now we need to bring in a loop and
iterate over the issue items which are
in the issues object and for each of the
issue item inside that array we need to
on generate the HTML code which is
needed to to produce the output we want
to have and that output needs to be
added to the inner HTML property of
issues worst and that's that's the way
how we are generating the dynamic or is
the output okay let's start
we're using a for loop and the for loop
is implemented by using for then we are
defining a variable e equals zero and
then we say he as less than
issues class okay he plopped us okay and
within that loop we are retrieving the
various properties so let's define
variable ID and we are assigning issues
with index E and we are using the
property ID here then let's say
description should equal issues
description okaying next thing is the
very key then we have assigned to take
the property and find two and finally we
are setting the status to issues index e
again and that status property okay okay
with all those variables label let's
generate the HTML output for that
element and we will type that output to
issues list inner HTML and subscribed
okay and the first thing we need is this
element and this element should get to
class well
okay let's close it so the next thing we
do need is a headline and the headline
will be embedded in an h6 text and the
headline is just printing out the he/she
ID okay and the issue ID of course is
available in ID okay so the next thing
is a paragraph and the paragraph should
output of the status information and the
status should be out put it by using a
good strap label and we can do it by
including a span element and assigning
all the classes label and ylabel info to
point it out in a light blue color and
okay then use the status variables you
include the status and concatenate
another string here with the
corresponding closing HTML text okay
okay next line is another headline close
this time h3 and we are outputting the
description okay let's close it and then
we need to output the severity
information let's do that by using
another paragraph and we want to output
the sorority information by including an
icon and bootstrap is providing a Nikon
set and we can use that by again using
the span element and give it a class of
glyphs click on this icon like so and in
that case we are using an icon which is
called glyphicon - type
okay those are concatenated of the value
of the variable severity and finally
let's close the paragraph okay
and next thing is assigned to again we
would like to output it by using not
only the assigned Q value but also an
icon it's the same thing so we can just
copy it from here okay the items of time
is not glyphicon - time it's called
glyphicon - user pays value assigned to
and let's close the paragraph again
finally let's add two buttons for each
armed element and one button should be
for setting the status to closed and the
other button should be for deleting the
issue item from from the list and from
local start and we do that by using an a
element setting the HLF value to
compound and assign in class of from
button and button warning in the first
case here okay
so let it should be the close button and
we are closing the element here the
second button
should be basically the same we are
changing the class button warning to
button danger and we are renaming the
button with delete ok and now for both
buttons we need to attach an event
handler function to you the on click
event and we do that by bringing in the
on click attribute and assigning the
method call we want to have so in that
case for the close button we want to
call a function which is named set that
is closed of course we need to implement
that function later on and in the second
case here we want to call function which
is called delete issue and of course
only calling the function without
passing any parameters is not sufficient
we need to pass in into that function or
the ID of the current element and we do
that here by using the following
backslash quote because we need to
escape it here quote plus Rd and plus
quote X slash for the second quote again
and now we can take that spring copy it
and insert it here and the call of the
delete issue function it as well ok now
one final string which needs to be
concatenated here and that's the closing
if element for the dish which has been
opened here at the beginning and that's
the last thing we need to concatenate
here and it's finally our string of HTML
code we are generating for each item
okay so let's switch back to index dot
HTML because now we want to make sure
that our function fetch issues is
executed one time when the application
is loaded and we can achieve that by
including here in the body element and
attribute and event attribute which is
called on load and assigning the call of
the fetch issues function here and let
make sure that such issues is called
each time the application who loads at
the moment you can see nothing has
changed so far no output has been
generated no issues are added to the
output that's ok because we have not
added any issues to local storage yet so
executing that function is retrieving
zero results okay so next let's
implement on the source code which is
needed to send data to local storage
each time the user thought of the form
and click on add and we are switching
over to main j/s and the first thing i'm
doing here is to add an event handler
which handles on the submit event from
our form and we can do so by saying
document dot get element by ID again and
i'm selecting the element we see rd
issue input form because that is the ID
of our form element and then I can say
dot add
event listener and want to respond to
you or the submit event type as the
first parameter I need to pattern here
and I'm attaching an event handler
method which I call let's say save issue
okay so let's implement the save issue
function next and do that here
save issue okay we are passing in a
parameter of e that's the event and the
first thing I'm doing I'm defining some
variables and designing the user input
values to and the variables so let's
start the first thing I need is the
issue description and I want to have the
well you need to user have type in into
the description field here in a memo
form and I can retrieve that value by
saying document and get element by ID
passing in the ID of the input element
that's in issue issue desk input and
then I would like to have value the same
for issue severity let's again say docu
mount get element by ID
this time we want to have the element
with CRD issue severity input and again
the value next issue assigned to get
element by ID and the ID is issue
[Music]
assigned to input okay
the value okay that's basically what I
need from my phone and then I need to
two other things I do need mm identifier
for that issue let's say you are issue
Rd and now I'm using the chance to
purchase library to generate a global
unique identifier for that new ID and
using that library is very easy I only
need to say chance but good and this
function is returning the global unique
identifier and assigning that identifier
now here to my issue ID arrival okay
then I need to the status and I will set
the status information to open because
open is the initial status okay okay now
we can put all those pieces of
information together and create a new
issue of the object so let's say well
issue and then assign an object with
properties of ID that OSU ID description
that should be real description severity
that should be issue severity okay I'm
assigned to that should be issue sign to
status should be put to issue status
okay okay now that we have the issue
object prepared we can continue
inserting that object to local storage
and we do that by first checking if
there is already something in local
storage and we do that by using the
local storage and object here and using
the method get' item and we get item I I
would leave the issue from a local
storage object that the object oh we
would like to store all our issues come
in and I check if this is now and if so
[Music]
let's initialize an empty array which is
called issues as well okay and then push
into that array our issue object from
above with all the properties filled
with the corresponding values and now
the array issues is containing exact one
element and now I can use the local
storage again this time with set item
and now I'm
setting issues with the key and I'm
setting that to the value to the Gaytan
representation of let's see string
string is high here on all our issues
array so the json dot stringify method
takes that array and generates a json
object and that is the value we are
storing in to the issues issues object
and local storage that's the key okay
okay now the L section and if we already
recognize that we have something in
local storage we need to insert our new
object and a slightly different way
first we need to retrieve everything
which is in local storage at the moment
and assistant I'm using JSON parsing and
then requesting from local storage which
get item again the issues object and I'm
getting it back in JSON format and then
I use case and pass to generate again an
array which I then assign two issues
here now we have everything in the
issues array which is a Weibull in local
storage and no again we can say issues
push issue or a new object so this is
extending the array one more element is
inserted and now I can send it back to
local storage so local storage again set
item okay like so into the issues key
and again I'm using JSON
[Music]
25 and passing in the issues array here
okay okay here we are that's basically
the code we need to insert our new issue
object into our local start but um
before finishing implementation of save
issue we need to do some final steps
here first let's reset our input
elements and we can use it very easily
by saying document.getelementbyid d
again I'm retrieving a reference to the
form element by using the a D issue
input form and then simply calling the
reset method this makes sure that
everything in the form is initialized
and the values are removed next I'm once
again calling fetch issues because now
with a new element inserted into local
search we'll need to call such issues
again so that the list output is
regenerated and the new element is
included in the list output as well and
finally I need to say here E is at the
event of the object and then call the
method prevent default just to prevent
default okay like so just to prevent the
form from submitting so that's basically
all what's needed here in save issues so
now let's check if everything is working
as expected here in our application I am
now using the form and type in the
information I need to create a new issue
so let's say
or a function of X and I set it to
medium and then I'm assigning myself and
then click on button add and now you can
see as expected the most output is
generated on here you can see we have
now one item on our list and it's output
in the way we wanted to on to show up
here we have VRD we have the status
information the description text the
severity the assigned to person and our
t buttons close and delete and of course
as we do not have implemented the event
handlers yet those buttons are not
working right now but that's the next
step and now to check once again that it
is stored in the local search you can
open up the developer tools here and go
to the tab application and here you can
see here is the possibility to take a
look into local storage for our
application here running on port 8080
and you can see we have one object term
with key issues inserted here and that
object on have a value that's our with
our ID and is containing all the values
belonging to our issue object okay so
let's continue with implementing the
missing pieces of our application and as
you might remember we have two more
things to implement earlier we have
defined here in our buttons to event
handler functions set the status to
closed for another close button and
delete issue for other lip button of
course and now we need to add both
implementations to our file manager yes
and we start by implementing the event
handler method set status to close so
okay it's a function of course and it's
called set that is closed and it needs
to take one parameter and that's the ID
of the issue item the user would like to
delete okay so on the first thing we
need to do is again retrieve everything
from local storage and put it into an
array which is called issues and again
we are using JSON path and seen before
local starch get item and the item we
would like to get is called issues again
okay next we need to iterate over all
the elements we have retrieved from
local storage which now inside that
array and compare the ID of each of
those elements to the ID which is passed
here into the method and if we have a
match between those IDs we know that is
the object we want to delete so let's
use the for loop here and let's say for
VAR e equals zero zero e less than shoes
length and the cluster okay
so let's do the comparison if issues
index e dot ID equals ID then we want to
delete it and there know not to leave it
on queue to set status to closed delete
will follow later on when we are
implement
the issue method so let's put the status
property to status closed okay that is
what we want to have here and now as the
change is made into the object which is
here still on the array we can now write
it back to a local storage and again
using the method set item and writing it
back to the issues key and using json
stringify to convert that array to json
format okay and finally don't forget to
call fetch issues again because we would
like to update our output here so that's
the implementation of set that is closed
okay so here we'll one typo that's
corrected and click fetch issue okay
let's try it out now we can try to for
that one item set the status from open
to closed by using that button here so
let's click close and you can see it
immediately set to closed and it's
updated with that new status information
in local storage as well and as we call
federal issues here at the end of our
sets that is closed method the output is
regenerated directly so that we can
immediately see that the new status is
available here in our user interface so
finally let's implement our second event
handler and that's the function with a
name
delete issue and again we need as a
parameter the ID of the issue we would
like to delete and for the
implementation I will copy on pass the
code
from the set that is closed event
handler and now it's basically the same
a first step is to retrieve everything
for me local storage stored in the
issues array and then iterate over all
the array items and compare VIPs and if
the ID is equal we know that we have
found all the issue which needs to be
deleted and now I only need to change
that line of code here instead of
setting the status information to close
I need to do something different and I'm
using the splice method to splice that
element out from bed array so it's index
II and I want to splice out one element
and so the element is removed from the
array and then it's L ed so the same
here I can write it back to local
storage and now with the element removed
and then call fetch issues again to
update the list output ok let's save it
and now we can try it out
now let's sir let's enter another issue
here so now it's error in function a and
now we are setting like to high play
let's edit here you can see a second
item in our list and I will now first
set that item to clear loans to play
again it's close and then I'm using
delete to delete it here thank you very
much for watching this was a bastion
from coding this Matt Wacom if you do
like my videos please don't forget to
subscribe to my channel here in YouTube
and also was it my website at coding
this mud wacom thank you very much again
see you the next time bye
[Music]